<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods new-yeeres gift sent vnto England, or, The summe of the Gospell. The first part contayned in these wordes, God so loued the world ... Iohn 3.16 / written by Samuel Nicholson ...</title>
            <author>Nicholson, Samuel, fl. 1600-1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1317</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22121695</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22121695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods new-yeeres gift sent vnto England, or, The summe of the Gospell. The first part contayned in these wordes, God so loued the world ... Iohn 3.16 / written by Samuel Nicholson ...</title>
                  <author>Nicholson, Samuel, fl. 1600-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Simon Stafford, dwelling in Hosier Lane neere Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸ C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John III, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Love --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25098:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS NEW-yeeres gift ſent vnto England: <hi>Or,</hi> The ſumme of the Goſpell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in theſe wordes; God ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but ſhould haue life euerlaſting, Iohn 3.16.</p>
            <p>The firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by Samuel Nicholſon, M. of Artes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by <hi>Simon Stafford,</hi> dwelling in Hoſier lane neere Smithfield. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25098:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25098:2"/>
            <head>Gods New-yeeres gift, ſent vnto England: <hi>Or,</hi> The ſumme of the Goſpell, contayned <hi>in theſe words:</hi> GOD ſo loued the world, that he hath giuen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but ſhould haue life euerlaſting, Iohn 3.16.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that writes himſelfe, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> &amp; <hi>Omega:</hi> the firſt and the laſt, ſignified thereby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is not onely the eternall Word, but alſo, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, middle, and end of the written word, yea, the ſcope of al the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Search the Scriptures</hi> (ſayth Chriſt:) <hi>for it is they that witneſſe of me.</hi> Euery line in them cryes out like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, Behold the Lambe of God.</hi> The Scriptures are a Circle, and Chriſt the Center, wherein all their prophecies méete. They are like the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Ianus,</hi> which looked forward &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. So the old Teſtament beheld Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:25098:3"/>to comes as <hi>Abraham ſaw his day, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> The new ſées him already come, as ſaith good father <hi>Simeon, For mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Chriſt is the contents of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: ſo the whole ſcripture ſéemes to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this verſe of my text. As all <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> brethren were feaſted with variety, but <hi>Beniamins</hi> meſſe excéeded them all: ſo al ſcripture is profitable; but this moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: all ſcripture is tryed gold; but this is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient pearle: ſo that heere the Euangeliſt ſéemes to propound all the word in a word. If thy memory be ſhort, here is a leſſon as ſhort as ſweet: ſo that it is doubtful, whether the quantity of the words, or their quality and worth, be more admirable.</p>
            <p>Theſe words are like precious Iewels, containing great riches in a little roome. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we vnlock the caſket wherein this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, let vs looke back to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py occaſion y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſt this wealth on our ſhores.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this comfortable ſcripture, was a conflict betwéene Verity and Vanity, light and darkneſſe, Chriſt and <hi>Nicodemus:</hi> for our Sauiour being that <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> that loues to communicate his goodneſſe with his creature; that Light that would
<pb facs="tcp:25098:3"/>lighten euery man that comes into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world; that <hi>Sunne</hi> that makes all things increaſe &amp; multiply; the <hi>Phyſicion</hi> that ſéekes out them that are ſicke; the <hi>Shepheard</hi> ſent to the loſt ſhéepe of Iſrael: his meate &amp; drinke was, to infuſe grace into men, and reduce ſoules vnto God. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he eate, but he brake the bread of Life? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he drinke, but he opened the fountaynes of Grace? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he walk, but he taught the wayes of GOD? When did he reſt, but he preached an euerlaſting Sabboth, and happy Iubilee to the penitent? Witneſſe ſo many Iourneyes, ſo many Sermone, ſo many Miracles: and witneſſe this preſent conſerence with <hi>Nicodemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Nicodemus</hi> being a better Lawper the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Goſpeller, one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> with <hi>Paul</hi> was brought vp at <hi>Gamaliels</hi> feet, but neuer ſate al Chriſts féete with <hi>Marie,</hi> ſeeking for light in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, comes vnto Chriſt by night.</p>
            <p>What might induce this great Doctour to come vnto Chriſt, is as full of ſuppoſes, as far from certaynty. Some thinke, <hi>Nicodemus</hi> came to tempt Chriſt, and therefore cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extols him, as the Wreſtler lifts vp his aduerſary, that hee may caſt him downe: Or as the <hi>Hyaena,</hi> who counterfayting a mans voyce, ſeekes to deſtroy him.
<pb facs="tcp:25098:4"/>Some thinke it was a ſiniſter influence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glory, that drewe this fantaſticke to Chriſt, as the Athenians into their excha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, only to heare newes. Some thinke <hi>Deriſion</hi> came to catch our Sauiour in a trap, that ſo raſh iudgement might conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him. Others preſume, that being affected with Chriſtes doctrine, hee came to gratulate our Sauiour, as the beſt ſort of our bad hearers, turne their owne profiting, into the praiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. But I thinke, this luke-warme louer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming ſo by night, was more afraid of the world, then affected with the Word, which he ſo praiſed: for <hi>Verus admirator virtutis, non borret Ariſtidis exilium, non Socratis condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. &amp;c.</hi> Howſoeuer, this Spider co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to ſuck poyſon from Chriſts wholeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, was at the length catcht in his owne net: for this plauſible Doctor, as if he had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Art of flattery, tips his inſinuating tongue with a triple praiſe, whoſe Syre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-voyce, aboue aboue al pernicious ſwéets in the world, tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles the very heart-ſtrings of man: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Ierome</hi> cries out, <hi>Happy is that ſoule, which is neither ſubiect to flatteries nor flatterings.</hi> And in <hi>Epiſt. ad Greg</hi> he ſaies, <hi>Nos ad patriam feſtinantes, mortiferos Syrenaris cantus ſurda aure tranſire debemꝰ.</hi> And <hi>Alanus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25098:4"/>ſaith, <hi>Quid ergo Adulationis vnctio, niſi dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum emunctio? quid commendationis alluſio, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prelatorum deluſio? <hi>What is the oyle of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, but the foyle of families? what the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of praiſe, but the infection of Prelates?</hi>
               </hi> But our Sauiour being thus aſſaulted by this Syren, ſhewes himſelfe like the <hi>Pſylli</hi> in Affrick, or the <hi>Marſij</hi> in Italy; who are not only themſelues ſafe from all venemous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, but haue alſe power to ſuck the poyſon from others infected. So Chriſt, who knew, that <hi>Laudari a laudato,</hi> was <hi>vera laus,</hi> would not applaud his vaine praiſe: for our Sauiour hauing got the ſubſtance, ſcorned the ſhadow; hauing in perfect action the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all vertues, refuſed the imperfect affection of vaine glory. Therefore <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was a foole, to buckle the light bladder of idle praiſe on his back, which was ordaind to beare the Croſſe of humility: he that loues vertue for praiſe, his mind is mercenary. We neuer read, that Chriſt euer admitted in him ſelfe this poyſon of humane praiſe, though ſhe often offred him her painted garland to adorne his vertues: whoſe perfection gaue a tongue of prayſes to his very foes; and out of the mouth of enuy, haue haled his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations: but finding in this blind Doctor, fit
<pb facs="tcp:25098:5"/>matter for his mercy to worke vpon, like a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Muſician, he caſts not away this iarring Iuſtrument; but after the correction of his folly, giues him inſtruction in the fayth: as the Phyſicion firſt lets out the hurtfull blood, and then miniſtreth wholeſome ſood. For though the Bull be offended with red, and the beſt ſometimes are not mended with roughneſſe: yet Chriſt knew, a ſharpe rebuke was a ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne remedy for <hi>Nicodemus.</hi> A child will eaſily grow with cheriſhing: but an old trée tranſplanted, will hardly proſper without pruning. Hony is ſtréet, yet it is ſharp where it findes a ſore. Though the budding Roſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with a mans breath, yet the Camomile muſt be trod on, to make it grow. He that is ſtung of the Aſpe, muſt haue the infected me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber cut off. The Ape killeth her young ones with too much cheriſhing: and the Iuie cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her ſupporter with too much imbracing. If <hi>Apelles</hi> ſhould ſée his <hi>Venus</hi> blemiſhed, or <hi>Protogenes</hi> his <hi>Hialyſus</hi> broken, ſurely the one would turne away his eyes, and the other throw away his Penſill. Then, ſhall we not allow Chriſt to be ſory, ſéeing his owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſo defaced through ignorance, &amp; ſo ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with errour? Yet Chriſt in his correction is like a kinde Nurſe, that whippes her cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:25098:5"/>Babe on the coate, not on the carkaſſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though he knittes his brow, he knittes in it a bleſſing: as the father holds an Apple in one hand, and a rodde in the other. But let vs firſt heare how Chriſt ſhakes his rodde at <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> roundly rebuking him for his blindneſſe in a chiefe poynt of Religion, the myſtery of Regeneration.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> art thou a Doctour in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and knoweſt not theſe things? Art thou a Teacher in Chriſts ſchoole, and haſt not yet learned Chriſts-Croſſe? How art thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a wiſe man in Iſrael, being a foole in Religion? There is no Wiſedome but the Trueth, <hi>in qua tenetur &amp; cernitur ſummum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. <hi>Salomon</hi>
               </hi> my ſeruant, in ſtead of riches, deſired of GOD the <hi>Spirit of Rule.</hi> If this was his prayer, much more ſhould it be thy wiſh, ſince hee was but King of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but thou art a corrector of ſoules. How canſt thou teach men to ſhun the ſecond death, which art ſo ignorant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond birth? A tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſhould be <hi>Organo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veritatis, <hi>the right hand of Truth,</hi>
               </hi> to miniſter to euery one, their food in due ſeaſon. Thou art an ouerſéer in Iſrael, &amp; art ſhamefully ouerſéene thy ſelfe. Now age hath ſnown down Winter on thy head, thoſe haires, which ſhould be Heraulds of wiſdom,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:6"/>ſhew thée to be twice a child. I would haue thée as a new borne babe, &amp; thou art a babe, not knowing newe birth. I would haue my Diſciples to ſhine as lights, but thou art a counterfeit Diamond, made precious by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foyle of <hi>Moyſes</hi> chaire, where thou art falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet. O <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> he muſt néeds be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils Doctor, that was neuer yet Gods Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple. I appeale to thy ſelfe, Is not a ſmall blemiſh in the face, more vgly then a great blot in the reſt of the body? He that combes himſelf, where ſhould he looke but in a glaſſe? And he that corrects himſelfe, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould he looke but on his elders? Though the Moone be dark, it ſhewes no great danger: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sun is eclipſed, it ſignifieth death. If the blinde lead the blinde, how can they but fall? Where the ſhip-maſter ſléepeth, who feares not ſinking? And where the ſhepheard wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not, the ſhéep go round to the ſhambles. Thou being a Doctor in Iſrael, thy lippes ſhould preſerue knowledge, &amp; thy life ſhould be the Lay-mans booke. If thy ſalt be vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nory, how wilt thou ſeaſon the ſimple? If thy rule be crooked, how canſt thou eyther di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the weak, or correct the wicked? Finally, if thy light be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe it ſelfe? Thou reſembleſt the heard
<pb facs="tcp:25098:6"/>
               <hi>Empetron,</hi> which the néerer it growes to the ſea, the leſſe ſalt it is: ſo thou, being a teacher in Iſrael, art a ſtranger in Iſrael. But why doe I reproue thy folly, and not rehearſe thy fault? Doeſt thou not know, <hi>Ad veram ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam peruenire non poſſunt, qui falſae ſuae ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae fiducia deſipiunt. <hi>They ſhall neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heauenly wiſdome, which hunt after it with humane wit.</hi>
               </hi> The Hart brags in vaine of his bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched hornes, becauſe he wants cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: and in vaine doeſt thou vaunt of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Domini,</hi> becauſe thou wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tſt knowledge. They which would ſee perfectly, winke on one eye. So, if thou wilt ſee the myſteries of God, thou muſt ſhut the eye of naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But no maruell thou art ſo dull: for as <hi>Cyclops exoculatus, manus quoque ver ſum porri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebat nullo certo ſcopo:</hi> ſo thy eye of faith being out, thy blinde reaſon gropes in the dark, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too ſhallow a Pilote to guide thée into the miſtery of Regeneration. I commend thee for thy ſkill in the lawe, but condemne thee for thy blindneſſe in the Goſpel. The ſeaman that eſcapes all ſyrtes and ſhelues, yet in the ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hauen ſuffers ſhip wrack, is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no leſſe fooliſh, then vnfortunate: and thou paſſing all the Labyrinthes of humane learning, yet comming ſhort of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:25098:7"/>of New birth, art to be pittied for thy fortune, &amp; derided for thy folly. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt I neuer alowed him that had all maner of knowledge, yet had not the meane of kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing. He that ſeekes knowledge, muſt note three things, <hi>Quo ordine, quo ſtudio, quo fine quaeque noſſeoporteat.</hi> The order of knowledge is to know that firſt, which brings ſooneſt to the way of ſaluation: the deſire in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt be to loue that knowledge chiefly, which moſt enforceth vs to loue: and the end of our knowledge, is not to win the praiſe of thy ſelfe, but to worke the profit of others. But alas, that which ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt in thy conſcience, is the fartheſt from thy care: that which ſhould haue poſſeſſed thy loue, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorſt from thy liking: &amp; that which ſhould haue bene the end of thy knowledge, is the beginning of thy ſhame. <hi>Qui Epiſcopatum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat, bonum opus deſider at.</hi> It ſeemes thou defireſt <hi>bonum,</hi> not <hi>opus;</hi> the worſhip, not the work: the goods of the fleece, not the good of the flock: elſe wouldſt thou not be ignorant in the very rudiments of Religion, &amp; fooliſhly build without a foundation. Thy comming to me, ſhewes in part thy loue; yet thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the night ſayes thy loue is but little: but I know, the flame when it kindleth, is
<pb facs="tcp:25098:7"/>mixed with ſmoke: and ſo is thy little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with the ſmoke of ignorance: yet I will not quench this ſmoking flaxe, nor break this bruſed reed: though y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> cameſt to me without buſines, thou ſhalt not depart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a bleſſing. As <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent his ſeruant with gifts in his hand, ſo I wil ſend thée hence with grace in thy heart: &amp; for thy <hi>3.</hi> idle pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I will repay thée <hi>3.</hi> endles profits: heare therefore the nature of Faith, the depth of Gods loue, &amp; the myſtery of Regeneration.</p>
            <p>Thus did our Sauior ſhake vp this fooliſh ſhadow of a Prophet, this idle eccho of his prayſes, this empty veſſell contayning no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the bare name of a Doctor in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el: whoſe example if we moralize, it teacheth vs, That (in Gods matters) the greateſt Clarks are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſeſt men. Philoſophers haue great wittes, but they are enemies to Grace. and the world hath her wiſdome, but it is enmity with God. Learning is a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarre, &amp; the knowledge of tongues is the key of truth: but if prophane learning turne <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer,</hi> and think to vſurpe <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, ſhee muſt be thruſt (with the Parret) out of <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Parliament. If <hi>Iſmael mocke Iſaac,</hi> though he be the ſonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he muſt be bauiſhed: And if Learning marre Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:8"/>though it be the gift of God, it muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned. The Starres giue ſome light, but the Moone muſt be miſtris of the night. As the poore Iſraelites borrowed of the Egyptians all their iewels, but to adorne themſelues: ſo we muſt borrow from profane Arts all their ornaments, &amp; with their ſpoyles adorne the Temple of God. So doing, Learning &amp; Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, like two twinnes, will liue and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And thus much touching the occaſion of theſe words.</p>
            <p>Hauing found out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hiue, let vs ſearch for the hony, contayned in this heauenly verſe:
<q>GOD ſo loued the world, that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but ſhould haue life euerlaſting, Iohn 3.16.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THeſe words contayne a Déede of giſt: which, for our better light, I branch into theſe ſixe parts. Firſt, the giuer, <hi>GOD.</hi> Second, the cauſe mouing him to this excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hounty, which is héere ſayd to bée <hi>Loue.</hi> Third, the gift: <hi>his onely begotten Sonne.</hi> Fourth, the party to whom this Legacie or gift is bequeathed: <hi>the World.</hi> Fifth, the fruite following this Gift, which is two-fold: firſt, a ranſome, in theſe words, <hi>ſhould not periſh:</hi> Secondly, a reward, in theſe words,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:8"/>
               <hi>ſhould haue life euerlaſting.</hi> Sixth, the hand where with we receyue this Gift, (namely Fayth) <hi>whoſoeuer beleeueth in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of GOD, the giuer.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, <hi>The giuer, GOD.</hi> The wealth of a Gift appeares in the worth of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: and if the giuer be baſe, the Gift is contemned: but if the giuer be gracious in our heart, the Gift is as precious in our eye. While our ſhips ride in our harbours, We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them not: but when they returne from the fartheſt Ocean, we looke for great riches. If a Meſſenger come to vs from a meane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we giue him meane entertaynement: but if a Prince ſend his worſt ſeruant vnto vs, we giue him princely regard. Well, <hi>God</hi> is richer then the Ocean, his boſome is full of bleſſings: <hi>God</hi> is greater then a Prince, his kingdom is euerlaſting: And as his thoughts are not as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thoughts, ſo his Gifts are not as mans gifts: for as he giues without me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo he giues without meaſure: he is excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in all his works. If he loue, it's without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: if he hate, his anger endures fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: if he giue, he powres down his bleſſings: if he take, <hi>non habenti, etiam quod habet, aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25098:9"/>he takes away al: He loues a cheareful giuer, &amp; ſhal we thinke him a fearfull giuer? A poore man on a time begging a groate of a King, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King ſnipt him with this anſwere, <hi>Non eſt Regium.</hi> If an earthly Prince thus ſtood on his gift, ſhall not the heauenly King regard what hee giueth? Chriſt telieth vs, that <hi>Beatius eſt dare, quàm accipere:</hi> it's a part of his Fathers bleſſedneſſe to giue. And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaies, <hi>Beneficium eſt beneuola actio tribuens, captanſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gaudium tribuendo,</hi> A bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or gift, is a worke of good will, that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as much in the giuing, as the receyuer doth in the gift. So then, if Gods gift bee a worke of good will towards man, wee may meaſure out his bene ficence by his beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, his worke by his wil, and his gift by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioy that hee taketh in giuing. When Gods loue intends a largeſſe, the gift muſt needs be great. The lower the vale, the more raine it receyueth: and the vnworthyer man is, the greater Gods loue is, and the richer his gift, In a word, the excellency of this gift ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in the excellency of the giuer, whoſe perſection is ſuch, as onely ſilence muſt ſhew it, while cencept and reaſon lie in a traunce through endleſſe admiration. A Philoſopher being commaunded to tell the King what
<pb facs="tcp:25098:9"/>God was, he aſked a dayes reſpit: and when the day was done, and the King expected his promiſe, he aſked two dayes: which being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he aſked foure daies, and after, eight. The King admiring his ſlackneſſe, demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded why he ſo abiourned his promiſe? Becauſe (quoth he) the more I think of him, the leſſe I know of him. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid eſt Deus? Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudo, Latitudo, ſublimitas, profundum: longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, propter aeternitatem: latitudo, propter charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: ſublimitas, propter maieſtatem: profundum, propter ſapientiam:</hi> and therefore as God is wonderfull, ſo are his gifts,</p>
               <p>Amongſt men indéede, the giuer may hee wicked, and the gift too. In the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>Numb. Balak</hi> was a wicked giuer, and ſo was his gift which he offced to curſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites. So in <hi>Acts 8. Simon Magus</hi> is a giuer, but a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed giuer: for he thought with gifts, to buy the gifts of Gods ſpirit. And ſuch giuers were the Phariſies: for they gaue <hi>30.</hi> pence to betray the Lord of life. But as <hi>Iudas</hi> receyued the earneſt peny of his perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo they betrayed their owne poſterity to endleſſe miſery. In a word, the Deuil himſelfe is a giuer, but a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked giuer: for he offred Chriſt all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world for an houres worſhip: as the Pope gaue all the New-found world to the Spaniards, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:25098:10"/>they ſhould worſhip him. But <hi>Dauid</hi> tels vs, <hi>Domini eſt terra.</hi> How ſhall the Deuill giue the world to Chriſt, that cannot giue himſelfe an houres reſpit from torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? His thorne yéelds no ſuch Grapes; his thiſtle beares no ſuch Figges, howſoeuer, like a bragging ſuitor, he boaſts of his riches: Though he promiſe an Angell of Light, hee payes with light An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and ſhall haue his portion with lewd An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in hell fire.</p>
               <p>But God, as he made all things good, ſo doeth he giue all things that are good. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>Omne bonum eſt Dei donum: Euery good gift, is Gods Gift.</hi> In <hi>Ieremie</hi> GOD ſayes, <hi>There is not an euill in the Citie, which I haue not created.</hi> If God create Euill for a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, much more doeth he create Good for our comfort. He is like the good father, that ſpends himſelfe in prouiding for his ſonne: or the kinde mother, which no ſooner hath a ſweet thing, but ſhe giues it her child: or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cunning Artificer, who cares not what coſt he beſtows on his worke, to make it more beautifull. So God is affected towards his creature: as he made all exceeding good, ſo he deſires y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good of all, eſpecially ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom he made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaſſe of his glory, &amp; the Image of himſelfe, to be his Sonne on earth, &amp; his Heire in heauen: and
<pb facs="tcp:25098:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>though here man is but tenant at will, yet he ſits at an eaſy rent, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bare debt of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes.</p>
               <p>The ſumme of this diſcourſe is, ſeeing God is the giuer of all good, we muſt look for all good things at his hands, &amp; deſire nothing that is good, farther then it is <hi>Gods gift:</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is ſnatcht from others, is the diuels bayte, not Gods bleſſing. The world is full of ſuch ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Nimrods,</hi> mighty hunters: for ſome hunt after Honour, ſome after Pleaſure, and ſome after profit: And theſe thrée Hunters haue almoſt hunted all Religion and Vertue out of our borders. But let them know, that, <hi>Quaedam dat Deus miſericorditer, quaedam finit habere iratus: <hi>Whatſoeuer comes by oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, tyranny, bribery, ſimony, or vſury, is not Gods gift, &amp; therefore no good gift, but a pledge of his anger.</hi>
                  </hi> Therefore whatſoeuer thou poſſeſſeſt or deſireſt, let conſcience be thy Cater, and the word thy warrant: ſo ſhall the tranſitories of this life, be vnto thée a handſel of heauen, and an earneſt penny of that bliſſe, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world neuer dreames of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of GODS Loue.</head>
               <p>THus hauing brought thée to the waters of life, namely, <hi>GOD the giuer,</hi> I will
<pb facs="tcp:25098:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhew thée the Welſpring of all bleſſings, <hi>his loue to the world, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The perſwading cauſe of this gift, is here ſayd to be <hi>Loue: God ſo loued. <hi>Quid eſt Amor</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith <hi>Aug.</hi>) <hi>niſi quaedam vita duo aliqua copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, vel copulare appetens, Amantem &amp; amatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>What is Loue, but as it were one life in two heartes, one ſoule in two bodies?</hi>
                  </hi> the Fire which bleſſeth where it burneth, the Soather which no arte can ſunder, the Knot which no time can vntye, the Hand which deſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſwéet muſike on the heart-ſtrings, the Cauſe which made God become man, &amp; the Vertue which makes man like vnto God: (I ſpeake not of that helliſh fire which makes men ſlaues, but of that heauenly Flame which makes them Saints.) As Chriſt was anoynted with the oyle of gladnes aboue his fellows; ſo this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is adorned with the crowne of eternity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all her fellowes: for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Fayth brings vs but to the Coffin, &amp; Hope watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the coarſe till the Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe two vertues are confined with our life, but our loue is refined by our death, and dwels with vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our glorification.</p>
               <p>But this our loue is but a ſhadow of Gods Loue, an Arme of his ſea, a drop of his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, a little flame of his liuing Fire; neither
<pb facs="tcp:25098:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>in quality ſo precious, nor in quantity ſo ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious by infinite degrées. God loues without cauſe; our loue is our duty: God loues vs his enemies; we loue him our friend: God loues without reward; our loue inherits heauen: God loues vs firſt; our loue payes him backe his owne: Gods loue is feruent; our loue is luke-warme: Gods loue is infinite; our loue is little, like our knowledge, &amp; low of ſtature like <hi>Zacheus.</hi> Chriſt muſt dine in our houſe, his loue muſt ſhine in our hearts, before we can reflect our borrowed heames, &amp; loue him againe. The excellency of this Gods loue can neither be expreſſed by our tongue, nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in our hearts: as it made the world of nothing: ſo the world is nothing to it: for it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all, &amp; is not comprehended of any. Our Sauiour heere thought beſt to expreſſe this Loue with a <hi>ſic dilexit,</hi> to ſhew vs, that his Father is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſick of loue: his deſcription is indefinite, becauſe his loue is infinite. Either Gods loue is ſo déepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt could not ſound it, or our reaſon ſo ſhallow that we cannot ſee it. As the Paynter that drew <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> ſorrowing for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his daughter, knew not how to figure his griefe in his face, and therefore drew a Vayle ouer it, thinking it impoſſible the gazers idle eye ſhould beholde
<pb facs="tcp:25098:12"/>what the fathers grieued heart could not hold: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt leaues that to our admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding cannot attayne. A holy Father would faine ayme at the dimenſions of this Loue, ſaying, <hi>Dilèxit Tantus tantillos: <hi>He a God of infinite maieſtie, loued vs men of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite miſery.</hi>
                  </hi> But this is <hi>obſcurum per obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius:</hi> for we know neyther <hi>quantus Deus, <hi>the greatnes of his Maieſtie,</hi>
                  </hi> nor yet <hi>quantuli nos: <hi>our grieuous miſery.</hi>
                  </hi> In a word, as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſée the Sunne but by his own light: ſo we cannot learne this Loue, but by Gods owne words. The Starre alone muſt lead y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to Chriſt, and Chriſt alone muſt lead vs to his Loue. Now whereas he expreſſeth it with a <hi>Sic: <hi>So GOD loued the world, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> a Father ſayth, This Aduerbe <hi>Sic,</hi> containes in it all Aduerbes of Loue: as if Chriſt had ſayd, My Father loued the world ſo dearely, ſo vehemently, ſo fatherly, ſo feruently, &amp;c. And <hi>Bernard</hi> on the Canticles ſayth, <hi>Deus ex ſe miſerandi ſumit materiem: <hi>Gods owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure is the motiue of his mercie.</hi>
                  </hi> Then he that can explaine Gods Nature, may expreſſe his Loue. Whereof to affirme the one, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and to performe the other, impoſſible.</p>
               <p>This is that Loue, (Chriſtian Reader) which in the zeale of God I comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to thine
<pb facs="tcp:25098:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>endleſſe admiration: this is the riches of his Grace, the chiefe of his Works, the ſumme df his Word, the ſhaddow of himſelfe, the perfection of his Glory. This teacheth our Fayth to ſtand, and our Hope to climbe, and our loue to burne: This cheereth our labors, and beareth our loſſes, and teacheth our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to ſmile. In a word, to this excéeding Loue alone, we owe our ſaluation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore damnable is the doctrine of the Church of Rome, that teacheth vs to erre both in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and matter of our Fayth: Firſt, in the maner, they teach vs to doubt of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. O iniurie intolerable, to doubt of the Promiſe, where ſuch a Loue is our warrant! What more frée then gift? or who more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then God the Giuer? Shall his Loue giue Chriſt vnto me, and my vnbeliefe thruſt him from me? Is the Trueth like vnto man, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſhould lye? or is his arme ſhortened, that he cannot ſaue? God forbid. This Gift is ſealed with the bloud of his Sonne, regiſtred in the ſight of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, witneſſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Angels, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an othe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. O incredulity, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wit of fooles, how many bleſſings dooſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bar vs from! Chriſt could not work his miracles, God ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſhew his mercy, where this mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte lurketh. Againe, in the matter of our faith
<pb facs="tcp:25098:13"/>they ſoyſt in moſt dangerouſly a lump of their owne Leauen: for God requires a Wedding garment to couer ſinne; they bring in a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous cloth: hee will haue vs build on his Loue; they would haue vs iuſtified by our own Labour: he will haue vs truſt to his Mercy; they would haue vs truſt in our merits. <hi>Pauls</hi> whole Epiſtle to the Romanes ſhoots only at this marke, to beat downe the pride of man, who would fayne be his owne ſaiour, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Nature, and extoll Grace: therefore in the end he addes this vpſhot, <hi>So then, wee are ſaued, not of works, but of grace.</hi> And <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſayth, <hi>Gratia eſt nullo modo, quae non eſt gratuita emni modo:</hi> Grace is all grace, or no grace at all. Againe be ſaith, <hi>Quiſquis tibi enumerat me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaſua, quid tibi enumerat, mſi munera tua?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Vis excidere gratta? Iacta merita tua,</hi> Our very Faith, as it's a grace in vs, is behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Grace: it ſaues, as it's a hand to lay hold on Chriſt, not, as it's a vertue &amp; a worke: for all works muſt humbly be caſt at Chriſts ſéete with <hi>Marie,</hi> &amp; there meitate on his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: they muſt not be buſy with <hi>Martha</hi> in the matter of our iuſtification. As God ſayd to <hi>Paul, My Grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> ſo I ſay to all, Gods Loue is ſufficient for you: this loue made you, when you were nothing; and
<pb facs="tcp:25098:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Loue muſt ſaue you, now your are worſe then nothing. Let the Papiſts clothe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the ragges of their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Iewes truſt to their <hi>Templum Domini,</hi> and the Heathen bragge of their paynted vertues, (which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calles <hi>ſplendida peccata</hi>) but let vs onely tryumph in this loue of God, and eſtéeme it the ſtrength of our ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Thus hauing diſcouered the rich treaſure of Gods loue, let vs know our duety, that we may bee accounted worthy to winne and to weare it. <hi>S. Auguſt. <hi>Lib. de Anima &amp; Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi>
                  </hi> ſéemes to ſtudy for this duty, ſaying, <hi>Miſer ego, quantum deberem diligere Deum meum, qui me fecit cum non era<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, redemit, cum perieram, &amp;c.</hi> O ſinfull wretch, how ſhall I requite the rare loue of God, who created me of nothing, and redéemed mee being worſe then nothing, &amp;c. And after, hauing found this duty out, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it to the world, <hi>Si non impendere, at repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere debemus,</hi> If we will beſtow no loue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, yet let vs repay his loue which hee hath ſhewed firſt. The world cries ſhame vpon an vngratefull perſon. If thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt trauell into a ſtrange Countrey, and there fall into the hands of théeues, and in méere compaſſion of thy miſery, the King of
<pb facs="tcp:25098:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Countrey ſhould ſet thée frée againe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thee life &amp; liberty, what would the world thinke? yea, what then wouldſt thou eſtéeme of thy ſelfe, if thou ſhouldſt prooue vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſo good a Prince? We are all ſtrangers in the world, and paſſengers from earth to heauen: now in our iourny we méet with the world and the deuill, and theſe rob vs of all grace, theſe wound vs and leaue vs for dead: now God of his excéeding mercy findes vs out, &amp; ſends his Sonne that good Samaritan, to powre the oyle of Grace into our wounds, &amp; to mount vs on the back of his merit, and ſo carry vs to the Inne of our reſt, the ioyes of heauen, O Loue, beyond all loue, how much thou art! O bleſſed God, teach vs the depth of thy Loue, that we may know the debt of our thankfulneſſe. Thine endleſſe bleſſing hath made vs bankrupts, for we are not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay the intereſt of thy loue. If we proffer our goods, alas, we receyued them of thée: If we offer our liues, they are redéemed by thée. Surely this ſhall bee our thankes, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy mercy: and ſince thy bleſſed Sonne hath taught vs, that the louing of thee, is the keeping of thy Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wee will labour to be all keepers: as we haue ſpent our time in the ſeruice of the
<pb facs="tcp:25098:14"/>world, the fleſh, and the deuill, ſo will wee ſpend the remnant of our dayes in the rebuke of ſinne, and the recording of thy Loue. And ſince the loue of ſo worthy a creature as man, is too coſtly a cyment to ioyne earth to earth, wee abandon all earthly deſires, and freely giue thee our hearts, and betroth our loue to thine.</p>
               <p>Deare God, by the fire of thy ſpirit, draw vp our affections to thée, diuorce vs from the liking of the world, and marry vs to the loue of thy ſonne: Let vs light our candle at thy Loue, &amp; learne by thy endleſſe mercy, neuer to end our thankfulneſſe, till death tranſlate vs from this vale of teares to Mount Sion, where our loue ſhal ioyne vs to thée eternally.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the Gift, CHRIST.</head>
               <p>NOw are we come to the Gift it ſelfe, the greateſt that euer was, whether we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bounty of God, or the bleſſing of man: for what could God giue greater then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? or what could man receiue better then his ſaluation? <hi>He hath giuen his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne.</hi> This bleſſed Gift is it that made <hi>Abraham</hi> reioyce, and the Angels ſing, and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> daunce in his mothers belly:
<pb facs="tcp:25098:15"/>this is able to make the World waxe young agayns, if Grace would open her eyes, and Wiſedome teach her to ſée her owne naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and the riches of this Garment ſent vnto her. As the Saints in heauen follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lambe whereſoeuer he goeth: ſo all the bleſſings of the earth follow Chriſt this Gift, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he goeth: for <hi>Habenti dabitur:</hi> He that hath this Gift, ſhall haue all other gifts, yea, he ſhall haue the Giuer too: for Chriſt ſayth, <hi>He that receyueth me, receyueth him that ſent me.</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſayth, <hi>Omnia habemus in Chriſto: ſi a vulnere curari deſideras, Medicus eſt: ſi febribus aeſtuas, fons eſt: ſi grauaris imquitate, Iuſtitia eſt: ſi indiges auxilio, virtus eſt: ſimortem times, vita eſt: ſi tenebras fugis, lux eſt: ſi coelum deſideras, via eſt: ſi cibu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quęris, alimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(He hath giuen.)</hi> God did not lend his Sonne, nor ſell him, but he gaue him to vs. Herein appeares the riches of his mercie, and the greatneſſe of our pouerty: he did not ſell him; we were not able to buy him; but he <hi>gaue him:</hi> which ſhewes vs to be beggers &amp; bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and that God muſt for pitty <hi>giue</hi> vs a Sauiour ſcanke &amp; frée, when we had neyther meanes to deſerue, nor grace to deſire him.</p>
               <p>(<hi>His onely begotten Sonne.</hi> He gaue vs not an Angell, nor a ſeruant, nor a creature,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:15"/>but <hi>his Sonne.</hi> The name of a ſonne is mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike in the eare of a father: &amp; the life of a child is more precious in the parents eye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne ſalety. Many parents, to ſaue their ſonnes life, haue willingly ſpilt their owns. Examples hereof we haue in profane &amp; ſacred Scriptures: we will take an handfull from a heape. In <hi>Gen. 37.</hi> when good father <hi>Iacob</hi> heard of the ſuppoſed death of his ſonne, (his wicked childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuing a falſe fire to his feare) he was ſmitten with ſorrow, riuers of teares guſhed out, and his heart bled at his eyes, for the ſuppoſed ſlaughter of <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his ſonne was too hot, to admit the cold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his other children: he that had wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with an Angell, could not wreſtle with this affection; and therefore in the griefe of a father, he ſets downe this reſolution: <hi>Ioſeph my ſonne is ſurely torne in pieces,</hi> and in my ſonne my ſelfe was torne: the claw of that beaſt hath rent my bléeding heart, &amp; his cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath killed two in one. O my ſonne, my life was ſhut in thy lookes, which now is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in thy loſſe: I made thée a coate of many colours, to ſhew, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou waſt the Raynebow pledge of my peace: but loe, the beauty of my Raynebow is rent, and in ſtead thereof, this bloudy Meteor appeares, ſhewing the death
<pb facs="tcp:25098:16"/>of my ioy, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuouring of my ſonne. The earth is made to couer the roote, not to containe the branch: I am the withered roote, my ſonne, &amp; thou the branch, whom vntimely death hath cropt. Why ſhould the graue bee deckt with gréene boughes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was made for gray haires? If children predeceaſe their parents, we are their of ſpring, &amp; they none of ours. Wel, ſince comfort wil not be my gheft, griefe ſhalbe my companion: &amp; ſéeing my ſonne forſakes me in my life, I will ouertake him in my death; for nothing but ſorrow ſhall bring my gray head to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> graue. Thus a good father mourned for a gracious ſonne: but will you heare a louing parents moane for a lewd child? In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>2. Sam. 18.</hi> when God purpoſed to chaſtice <hi>Dauid,</hi> he made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne to whip the father: for <hi>Abſolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that by name ſhould haue bin his fathers ioy, by nature proued a Parricide, &amp; ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his owne ſyre: but God hauing ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbled <hi>Dauid</hi> his child, threw the rod in the fire, and brought a iudgement vpon <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> which coſt him his life. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>Dauid</hi> being mooued with the good affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a father, more then the bad condition of his ſonne, was ſo far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioycing in <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms</hi> death, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it almoſt coſt him his own life. <hi>O Abſolom my ſonne</hi> (quoth he) <hi>would God
<pb facs="tcp:25098:16"/>I had dyed for thee; O Abſolom, my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi> But God héere is neither like <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting a good ſonne, nor <hi>Dauid</hi> beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a wicked child: he reſembles good <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> who willingly ſacrificed his ſonne <hi>Iſaak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was much, to giue a ſonne: yet as if this were not enough to expreſſe Gods loue, the holy Ghoſt addeth, <hi>his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne:</hi> he gaue not an adopted ſonne, as <hi>Abraham</hi> offred a Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me in ſtead of <hi>Iſaac:</hi> but his owne ſonne. And herein appeares his perfect iuſtice, a bleſſed preſident to all Iuſticiaries. In all Gods actions this vertue ſwayes: though his mercy be aboue all his works, yet mercy and iuſtice muſt kiſſe together. The deareſt drop of Chriſts blood muſt be ſhed, before GODS inſtice be left vnſatiſfied.</p>
               <p>Nay, this was not enough to ſatiſſy Gods mercy; his loue mounts a degrée higher, and further it cannot aſcend. <hi>He gaue his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sonne.</hi> When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world could not yéeld the price of our redemption, he ſearched his owne boſome for a Sauiour, &amp; gaue vs <hi>his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne.</hi> If God had many ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, his mercy had bene meaner, &amp; his loue had ſéemed leſſe: but he gaue vs not one ſon of many, but one &amp; all, <hi>his only Sonne</hi> (for whoſe ſake, he ſpared not his Angels) his delight, his boſome frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:17"/>the image of himſelfe, for the ranſome of the world.</p>
               <p>O loue beyond all loue, how much thou art! A holy father in admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this loue, cries, <hi>Quàm diues es in miſericordia, quàm magnificus in iuſticia, quàm munificus in gratia, Domine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us noster!</hi> Againe, <hi>Paſsio tua, Domine Ieſu, vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt refugium, ſingulare remediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: deficiente ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia, Iuſtitia non ſufficiente, ſanctiatis ſuccum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentibus meritis, illa ſuccurrit: cum enim defecerit virtus mea, non conturbor: ſcio quid faciam, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum ſalutaris accipiam, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inſtruction that we muſt learne from the conſideration of this vnſpeakeable Gift Chriſt, is two-fold: Firſt, wee are taught to returne our loue againe, as <hi>Aug.</hi> ſayes, <hi>Sinon am are, ſaltem redam are debemus:</hi> As GOD hath giuen vs his <hi>onely Sonne,</hi> ſo we muſt ſhow our reciprocall loue to God, and for his <hi>Sonne,</hi> giue him our ſelues: as he hath giuen vs wealth, we muſt beſtowe our wealth on him agayne: as he hath giuen vs liberty, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, children, long life, knowledge, wiſdom, courage, &amp;c. theſe muſt all wayte on him, and doe him honour and ſeruice: Thus we muſt giue him loue for loue, agayne.</p>
               <p>The ſecond vſe of Gods vnſpeakable bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is, to teach vs to loue our brethren.
<pb facs="tcp:25098:17"/>Chriſt teacheth vs this leſſon for his Loue, ſaying, <hi>I haue giuen you an example how to loue one another.</hi> Brethren muſt be vnited in the bond of mutuall loue, like <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians Fagot: for the vnity of brothers is, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce quàm iucunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> excéeding ioy to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints. But alas, let vs ſee what Louers, and what Giuers our wicked age doth afford. When I ſtudy vpon this duty, I find foure ſorts of Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: The firſt &amp; the worſt ſort, haue the hand to giue, but not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart to graunt: of whom I may ſay as Chriſt ſayd, <hi>Better this hand were cut off,</hi> &amp; they were as poore as <hi>Irus,</hi> then with their ruſting riches <hi>to be caſt into Hell.</hi> Theſe are the Mammoniſts of our age, whoſe ſoule lies treaſured w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their ruſting pence, who are more vnmercyful the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuill, for he would haue Chriſt turne ſtones into bread: but theſe men turne bread into ſtones, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bread of the poore, into ſtone walles, or elſe ſpend it on their accurſed luſts, forgetting mercy: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore damnation attends the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſecond fore haue the heart, but not the hand; whoſe myts God accepts aboue all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mines of the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, &amp; takes their loue for their largeſſe. The third ſort, are ſuch as haue neither heart nor hand in this duty; &amp; theſe are poore men euery way: for he that can bring forth neither good
<pb facs="tcp:25098:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>work, nor good wil, is a dead me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in Chriſts Body, &amp; ſhall be cut off. The fourth ſort, haue both hand &amp; heart; &amp; theſe walke in brotherly loue; theſe are they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walk worthy of this Gift Chriſt, &amp; ſhal haue their déeds of mercy, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwéete harueſt ſong, <hi>Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father, poſſeſſe the kingdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you from the beginning of the world: for I was hungry, and ye gaue me meate, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. Of the world.</head>
               <p>NOwe it remaynes, that we conſider, to whom this great Legacie is bequeathed. The world. What, is the world ſome friend of Gods? No. What, is God indebted to the world? No. What is the world? The world is named and taken diuers wayes: firſt, <hi>pro soto creato, <hi>Iohn. 1.10. Heb. 11.3.</hi>
                  </hi> ſecondly, <hi>pro mundo damnato. <hi>Ioh. 17.9.</hi>
                  </hi> thirdly, <hi>pro ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine mundato, <hi>Rom. 5.10. Col. 1.20.2. Cor. 5.19.</hi>
                  </hi> and ſo it is taken in this place: for the world here meant, is a certaine ſmall number of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> which God, of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable clemency, hath ſet apart, to exerciſe his mercy vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and hath choſen them out of the ſame lumpe &amp; maſſe that the damned world is of, euen all alike firebrands of hell,
<pb facs="tcp:25098:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>fellowes with the falling Angels; all alike Traytours, Rebels, incarnate Deuils: for <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Quod tuum eſt, Sathanas eſt:</hi> Euery man is of himſelfe a deuill. Will you heare what Gods iudgement &amp; opinion is of the world, as men are in themſelues? In the 145. Pſalme, God takes a view of man, and then ſayes, <hi>Homo vanitati ſimilis factus eſt:</hi> Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is become like vanity. As if he had ſaid, Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I made man, I made him to mine owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I had a pleaſure to looke on him againe and againe; I held my workmanſhip excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good, <hi>Gen. 1:</hi> But lo, man hath mard what I haue made, he hath befaeed mine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, &amp; hath made himſelfe like vnto vanity: nay, he hath ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g delighted in vantly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now he is vanity it ſelf, <hi>Pſal, 39.5.</hi> In <hi>Iob 1.</hi> It is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Naked I came out of my mothers wob:</hi> yea (ſaith a holy Father) <hi>naked</hi> of all grace &amp; vertne. In <hi>1. Cor. 3.</hi> it's ſaid, <hi>The wiſdom</hi> of <hi>the world is fooliſhnes with God.</hi> How is it then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God beſtowes this great Legacy vpon ſooles? we know, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willingly leaues his land to a foole. I anſwere, This amplifyes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God, who hath choſen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fooliſh <hi>things of the world, &amp;c.</hi> Again, <hi>1. Cor. 2. Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>The carnal man vnderſtands not the things of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od.</hi> How then? Why ſurely, <hi>Ignoti nulla cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25098:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>what a man vnderſtands not he neyther deſtres, nor delites in. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world was as worthy of this great preſent, as ſwine are of pearles; or the ſwiniſh Gergeſenes were of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, when they willed him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of their coaſts. Againe, <hi>Iob. 15.16.</hi> it's ſayd, <hi>The heauens are vncleane in Gods ſight, how much more is man abominable &amp; filthy, which drinketh iniquity like vnto wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> Le here, fieſh &amp; blood, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wretched offpring of <hi>Adam,</hi> conſider here, thou vnworthy world, &amp; tell me what thou waſt, when Gods mercy found thée out. O Loue, beyond all loue, how much y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art! Man, abominable and filthy man, is fit matter for Gods mercy to worke on: Man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drinketh iniquity like vnto water, is thought worthy to drink of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waters of Life. In this ſaying, <hi>Iob</hi> doth anatomize y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, calling it abominable &amp; filthy. But will you ſée a more exact Anatomy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, lym me by lymme? <hi>Paul,</hi> to the <hi>Gal. 5.</hi> rips vp the hody of the world, &amp; there finds in it a whole den of deuils: the works of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world (ſaith he) are, <hi>Adultery, fornication, vncleannes, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, Idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, debate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wrath, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions, ſeditions, hereſies, enuy, murthers, drunkennes, gluttony, &amp;c</hi> Here are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuils which God muſt caſt out
<pb facs="tcp:25098:19"/>the world, as he did the buyers &amp; ſellers out of his Temple, if he will reconcile the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The Apoſtle brings the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in by ranks, as if hel were broke looſe, or as if this later world were ſo wicked, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eyther deuils ſéemed to be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, or men into deuils. And this ſignifies S. <hi>Iohns</hi> ſaying, <hi>Totus mundus in maligno poſitus:</hi> the whole world is ſet on miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>To conclude this <hi>4.</hi> poynt of the vnworthines of the world, to whom God hath giuen this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy. This Vnworthynes ſhall appeare moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, if we conſider the Iewes, a choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> part of the world, or rather, a people choſen from the world; let vs, I ſay, conſider in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world is, &amp; how vnworthy of ſuch a preſent. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God had ſent this vnſpeakeable Gift of <hi>his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne</hi> to the Iewes, by the hands of his ſeruants, the Prophets, they tooke his ſeruants, &amp; beat ſome, and kild ſome, and ſtoned others. God ſent againe his Prophets, &amp; they vſed them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. The louing mercy of God looke no vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at this; but at laſt, ſent to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Gift by the hand of <hi>his only Sonne,</hi> thinking ſurely, Though they regard not my Gift, yet they will reuerence my Sonne. But how did they reuerence him? <hi>This is the heire</hi> (ſay they) <hi>come, let vs kil him, &amp; the inheritance ſhall be ours.</hi> Chriſt was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orne, but they ſought his life: how was hee
<pb facs="tcp:25098:20"/>entertained, reuiled, blaſphemed, perſecuted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, hunted too &amp; fro, haled before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, accuſed in <hi>2.</hi> Conſiſtories, &amp; there reuiled, ſmitten, condemned, &amp; at laſt moſt cruelly done to death? Behold here the deſert of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, behold here to whom God hath ſent his Sonne: conſider this vprightly, &amp; thou will cry out with <hi>Dauid, Lord, what is man, that thou regardeſt him?</hi> what is eyther Iewe or Gentile, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou reſpecteſt him? If thou wilt néeds ſhew ſuch Loue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew it to thy holy Angels, who honour thée; to thy goodly creatures, the Sunne, the Moone, &amp; ſtarres, who neuer did offend thée: onely man is the ſinner in this world, and he alone taſtes of thy goodneſſe. I. this is mercy, Lord, to ſaue, where y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mighteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; to ſalue, where thou findeſt ſicke; to helpe, where y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> findeſt néed; to forgiue our ſinnes, while we forget our thanks; &amp; to giue vs heauen, who haue deſerued hell. As the ſtarres ſhine cleareſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darkeſt night, ſo thy mercy appeares whiteſt being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with the blacknes of our deſerts. Thou didſt viſit vs, when we were nothing but banity: thou didſt clothe vs in the righteouſnes of thy Sonne, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were al naked of grace, thou didſt inſtruct vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were fooles, and heaie vs when we were abominable &amp; filthy: thou didſt ſéeke vs when we knew thée not, &amp; find vs when we had loſt our ſelues: thou didſt ſet thy hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25098:20"/>vs, when our hearts were ſet on miſchieſe: thou didſt pray for vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we perſscuted thée; &amp; dyed for vs, when we hated thée; &amp; thirſt our ſaluation, when we thirſted thy hlood: thou haſt ranſomed vs from hell, &amp; rewarded vs with heauen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to thée Lord, to thée, will we ſing a new ſong, and reioyce in the <hi>ſtrength of our ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are taught fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this <hi>4.</hi> poynt, the excéeding riches of Gods mercy. And to come home to our ſelues; what were we before this Gift was ſent to vs by the moſt happy reigne of our dreas So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne? As <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent not his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gifts, when he went to take a wife for <hi>Iſaac;</hi> ſo God ſent not Religion empty-handed into our Land, but accompanied with a vertuous Prince, and gracious Mother of this our Iſrael; and all, to woo and winne vs an vnſpotted Spouſe to our <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Chriſt. But what were we, I ſay, to whom God hath ſhewed ſuch mercy, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this Text ſéemes to be ſpoken of vs, <hi>So God loued England, that he hath giuen, &amp;c?</hi> What were we, when his Loue ſought vs, &amp; his mercy found vs out? Were we not blinde Idolaters, horrible back-ſliders, &amp; cruell murtherers of his Saintes? For theſe ſinnes he caſt off his people the Iewes; and yet, with theſe ſinnes hath he choſen vs. As a man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wife with all her infirmities: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> taken vs with all our faults: our blind Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry
<pb facs="tcp:25098:21"/>and horrible rebellion; our wilfull ignorante and wicked reſiſtance; our prophane liues &amp; polin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſciences; our hate of the fruth, &amp; loue vnto lyes; our following y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, &amp; forſaking of Chriſt; all this was but matter for Gods mercy to work on. So that we may ſay with <hi>Dauid, Lord, what is man, that thou regardeſt him?</hi> Lord, what is England, that thou reſpecteſt it? this poore frozen corner of the North, that thou art mindful of vs? We are froſt-bitten Snakes, wormes, &amp; no men, whom thou haſt ſo pittifully cheriſhed in thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. If hate deſerue loue, if cruelty merit kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, if finne purchaſe pardon, if murther require mercy: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt is our due, then God is our deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, then heauen is our owne. But, Lord, our hearts tels vs, that we are this vn worthy world; our liues witneſſe, that hell is our portion, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is our due: but eternall Life is the Gift of GOD in Chriſt: To whom with thee, and the holy Choſt, hee all prayſe, honour, and glorie, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:25098:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
